<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England must pay the piper being a seasonable discourse about raising of money this session : in a letter to a member of the honourable House of Commons.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38371</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2935</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27351</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09818645</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09818645</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38371)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1356:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England must pay the piper being a seasonable discourse about raising of money this session : in a letter to a member of the honourable House of Commons.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697 --  Finance, commerce, confiscations, etc.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Military --  1603-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:44173:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44173:1"/>
            <head>ENGLAND <hi>Muſt Pay the Piper.</hi> BEING A SEASONABLE DISCOURSE ABOUT Raiſing of Money this SESSION. In a Letter to a Member of the Honourable Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>ACcording to your commands I waited upon Sir</hi> R. W. <hi>at his return from the Country, and diſcourſed him concerning the matter you gave me in charge about raiſing of mony this Seſſion of Parliament, and found him ſo prepared to give me ſatisfaction therein, that he had Writ a ſmall Tract on that Subject, which he was ſo Obliging to lend to me to Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, which I here ſend you without any Alteration; he having deſigned it for a member of Parliament; and it is as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Think it paſt Diſpute, that there is not one man of an hundred who would in any manner have contributed to this Revolution, if they could have foreſeen, that thereby we ſhould have been engaged in ſo durable, expenſive, and deſtructive a War, in Defence of the Dutch, and other Confederates; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the eternal Scandal of our Loyalty, Religion, Honeſty, Juſtice, Honour, and Morality; but to the Waſte and Conſumption of our Stores of Arms and Ammunition, the Loſs of our Ships and Men, the Inundation of Foreign Force, to the very enſlaving the Nation to their Intereſt, Councils, and Conduct, and the utter beggering of our ſelves, by the Decay of Traffick and inſupportable Taxes.</p>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:44173:2"/>
                     <p>Yet all this might have been more pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently born, if we had found a ſincere and cordial Proſecution of the glorious Ends which were pretended, of a full Enjoyment of our Chriſtian and Civil Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Properties, as true, free-born Engliſhmen, which were ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (as things invaded in the late Reign,) to be taken ſpecial care of.</p>
                     <p>How far we have been diſappointed in theſe particulars, may be the ſubject of another Diſcourſe; reſolving at preſent to confine my ſelf onely to the Queſtion about raiſing of Money.</p>
                     <p>Since my going into the Countrey I have ſadly experienced to what Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences the Farmers and Tenants are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, by the Decay of Trade, the Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Markets in Corn, Cattel, and Wool; the Squeezing of their Purſes to the utmoſt Mite, by ſucceſſive and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled Polls and Taxes; the Haraffing the whole <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdom, to the Expence of more than two Poll-bills more, when the Council knew full well that the French Fleet had no Land-men on board to make a deſcent; to which may be added, the univerſal Preſſing of Labourers and Servants, whereby neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Hands were wanting for Tillage and Harveſt. From hence it is that we can neither get our Rents, nor the Countrey men Money for their neceſſary ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                     <p>In this their deplorable Condition they are almoſt ſunk into deſpair, at the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence given them of a Debt of four or five Millions yet remaining, after the ſix Millions paid by them, or raiſed out of the Revenue; and that this muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be advanced this Seſſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a Fund of three Millions more the next Spring, for the enſuing Campaign.</p>
                     <p>You very well know, that it was the expectation of the Commonalty of the Kingdom, that at the laſt Meeting of the Parliament they would have perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Bill of Commiſſion of Enquiry for the Money already given, how it had been expended. Your Fellow Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners challenge at your hands a ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in this particular, before you give a farther Supply; and this with the ſtricteſt Examination.</p>
                     <p>And ſince we are ſo inclinable to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue Dutch Councils, and eſpouſe their Intereſt; it is but reaſonable we ſhould likewiſe imitate their Conſtitution; eſpecially in this particular of Raiſing Money, not to determine it before the Commons (as their States do in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of greateſt Moment) conſult, and obtain the Approbation of all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Cities, and Burroughs; which, if ever, at this Juncture is moſt requiſite, and would be the greateſt Inſtance of the People's true Liberty, that ever had been granted by any of our Kings, in confirmations of our <hi>Magna Charta.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This they judge the more reaſonable and juſt, becauſe it is every where brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the Officers both at Sea and Land, eſpecially the Engliſh, are nine or eleven Months in Arrears of Pay. I have it from a Captain, who ſerved in <hi>Ireland</hi> under all the Hardſhips of Duke <hi>Schomberg</hi>'s Campaign, that when they arrived at <hi>Dublin,</hi> they had but three Months Pay of thirteen then owing to them, with a Complement, that they ſhould ſtay there to ſpend it.</p>
                     <p>Beſides this, we are told of the vaſt Summs owing for Money taken up at Bankrupts Intereſt, and for Proviſions alſo of Ammunition, taken up on Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit at exceſſive Rates; and farther, I am told, that if we had not ſeized the <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh</hi> Ships, laden with Maſts, Pitch, Tar, and Materials for Cordage, we could not out of our exhauſted Stores, have rigged out our Fleet at this Seaſon, when it was well known, how infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provided it was two years ſince.</p>
                     <p>Farthermore, the Common Soldiers make a general Complaint, that they ſcarcely have had ſubſiſtence Money, whereby they have been neceſſitated, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take free quarter, or rob and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, or over-awe their Hoſts to take what they would pleaſe to give them, though ſome are ſo good natured as to pawn their Coats and Hats for Bread and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44173:2"/> Drink: All which conduceth to the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impoveriſhing of the Countrey.</p>
                     <p>It muſt indeed be owned, that it may be thro' a politic Deſign, the Officers are thus treated, whereby they may be kept in a ſtricter dependence on the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for fear, leſt if they ſhould quit the Service, they might loſe their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears; and many dying, by Sickneſs or Battel, will ſave the publick ſo much as is owing to them; for I believe you can find few Inſtances, that any Heirs or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutors, Widows or Orphans, were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the Legacies of Arrears, either left by Officers, or Common Soldiers, or Seamen. Upon the whole, I find that many inquiſitive and judicious Perſons, calculating the Income of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and the Expence, are of opinion, that there is no reaſon for ſuch Arrears, but think it demonſtrable that either there is ſome ſecret <hi>Agreement,</hi> which muſt be concealed from the Nation, to furniſh the Confederates with Summs of Money from hence, or that the foreign Troops are better paid than the Engliſh, or that by Combination Treaſures are hoarded up by our Miniſters of State for a comfortable Subſiſtence againſt a Storm.</p>
                     <p>It hath ever been the care, as it is the Duty of the Houſe of Commons, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the publick Wants of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with Money proportionable to the neceſſities of Affairs: But withall they have been carefull in all Kings Reigns, to ſee that the Money ſo given was tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expended, for thoſe ends for which it was given. And they have ſtifly denied Supplies, till they were ſatisfied in the neceſſity, and with the publick Emolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which was like to accrew to the Common-wealth by ſuch Expence, and have been allways carefull to avoid fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Councils and Forces, from having Influence over the Government. And when upon weighty Conſiderations they have thought it expedient to give Money, they have taken ſpecial care to intruſt the Managery thereof in ſafe Hands, as may be found, upon all ſuch occaſions, in the Journals of the Houſe; otherwiſe they deſerved not to be the People's Repreſentatives and Truſtees.</p>
                     <p>You know full well you have been ſingled out, upon ſpecial confidence in you, to prepare and conſent, on their behalf, to ſuch Laws as are for publick benefit; yet it is well known, that in the reſpective Countries you leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind you a much greater number of Perſons of Quality, no ways inferiour to your ſelves in Eſtates, Intereſt, and love of their Countrey's Proſperity; ſo that in common prudence, you ought to have regard how you oppreſs them, their Relations, Friends and Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore in the matter of Money, you ought, in reſpect to them as well as your own Poſterities, to ſuſpend your giving of Money till you be able to give them ſufficient ſatisfaction, that what hath been given is truly expended, and that the raiſing of more is for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good of the Commonwealth of the Kingdom.</p>
                     <p>I preſume the Inducement which will ſway you moſt in this matter, will be that <hi>Ireland</hi> may be ſubdued, and that <hi>France</hi> may be brought to ſo low a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that the King thereof may be compelled to yield to the Emperour, the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and other the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, what ever he hath by his Arms diſpoſſeſſed them of.</p>
                     <p>If therefore I make it appear, that it hath not been the aim of ſuch as have influenced our Affairs, to reduce <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but rather, as it appears by the conſequence of things, the Deſign hath been, under that Pretext, to raiſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to diſtribute amongſt the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, according to ſome ſecret Articles not communicated to the Houſes, and to purchaſe at any rate foreign Forces, to the great hazard of the enſlaving us to them. And if I make it appear that without the Confederates will bear a conſiderable part of our Charge, we ſhall not be able to keep in conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with them; or can, though we
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44173:3"/> ſhould pawn our Eſtates to raiſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, be able to bring <hi>France</hi> to terms, as affairs are managed abroad. If, I ſay, I clear theſe two Points to your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, I hope you will then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the giving more Money will be but powring Oyl into the Fire, which will finally conſume us.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall begin with <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is well known that when the P. of <hi>O.</hi> took upon him the Adminiſtration of the Government, before the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had conferred upon him the Regal Title, the Proteſtant Intereſt in <hi>Ireland</hi> was little inferiour to that of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks, and a ſmall Supply from hence would have caſt the Scales.</p>
                     <p>There are Noblemen who can tell, if they pleaſe, that even then an Overture was made, that upon diſtributing 30000 <hi>li.</hi> among certain Officers in <hi>Ireland,</hi> they would have undertaken that the Army there ſhould have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. And it is as well known to thoſe Noble Perſons who it was that would not allow above 20000 <hi>li.</hi> to be expended on that account, and ſo the Project fell: But we have reaſon to believe, that to ſupport the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Intereſt, twenty times as much hath been disburſed to <hi>Germanes, Danes,</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> to the <hi>Swiſs-Cantons,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and other Allies.</p>
                     <p>It is worth a ſerious Enquiry, whence it happened, that Collonel <hi>Lundy,</hi> who was accuſed for having treacherouſly deſerted the Defence of <hi>London-Derry,</hi> and Col. <hi>Richards,</hi> and <hi>Cunningham,</hi> who were charged with Cowardiſe, in not adventuring to conduct the Forces under their Command to the Relief of the ſame, were onely impriſoned and caſhiered, but were never brought to any Tryall. Or why M. G. <hi>Kirk</hi> lay ſix Weeks in <hi>Lough Foyle,</hi> without attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to relieve the Town, till 5000 of the Soldiers and Townſmen were dead by Famine and Sickneſs; yet when it was reduced to the laſt Extremity, he found it no difficult work to ſend in Supplies.</p>
                     <p>When D. <hi>Schomberg</hi> went to <hi>Ireland,</hi> he carried with him an Army ſufficient to have vanquiſhed a much greater force than King <hi>James</hi> then had, conſidering they were neither diſciplin'd, arm'd, nor provided with Artillery or Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition in any Plenty at that time; ſo that he might with much facility have then marched to <hi>Dublin,</hi> the Soldiers being exceeding earneſt for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. But, it ſeems, it was not then thought ſeaſonable to effect ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a Work; but that great <hi>General,</hi> very adviſedly, ſuffered two parts of his Army to periſh in the moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner that ever Engliſh-men did in their own Camp.</p>
                     <p>Let us now reflect upon what hath been done ſince the Succeſs at the <hi>Boyne.</hi> When K. <hi>James</hi> was fled, and, as our publick Intelligences informed us, there were not 2000 Iriſh left in a Body; Was this Victory purſued? Or the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted Iriſh cloſely followed? No, they had time given them to rally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, about <hi>Athlone, Limmerick,</hi> and <hi>Galloway.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To this may be added, that Duke <hi>Schomberg</hi> declined the arming of the Iriſh Proteſtants, till abſolute Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty compelled him to it, for the Recruit of his Army, and the like was denied after advancing beyond <hi>Dublin;</hi> till the News came of the Defeat the French had given us at Sea: Whereas thoſe Men, both for their Zeal to the Cauſe, and their Experience in the Countrey, as well as unaptneſs to the Diſeaſes of the Climate, might have been of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt uſe, if a ſpeedy reducing of that Kingdom had been deſigned.</p>
                     <p>It muſt be owned that there were ſome, who truly deſiring Diſpatch, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that a Proclamation might be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, whereby ſuch Terms might be afforded, as the Iriſh, during their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation, might be the likelieſt to comply with; and thereupon yield up their Arms, and Strong Holds: For which purpoſe it was propoſed, that ſuch as ſo ſubmitted, might be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44173:3"/> Life, and enjoy their Eſtates ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Settlement in K. <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d's time; impoſing ſome pecunia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Mulcts on ſome few of the moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, and that an Indempnity ſhould be granted to the common ſort, upon yielding their Arms, and obliging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Obedience.</p>
                     <p>But this was oppoſed, and it is known by whom, upon a Reaſon well worthy Obſervation, <hi>viz. That a Promiſe had been made to the Counts and Officers, Germanes, Danes, and Dutch, that they ſhould have Lands diſtributed among them, after the Conqueſt of the Countrey:</hi> Which Promiſe could not be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, if any of the Iriſh who had been in Arms, were permitted to enjoy their Eſtates.</p>
                     <p>From hence we may learn the true reaſon why the Dutch and Danes brought over ſo many hundreds of Women and Children, who went over to <hi>Ireland</hi> with the Army, no doubt on Promiſe of ſharing that Kingdom, and planting Dutch and Daniſh Colonies, as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of their Service.</p>
                     <p>Upon thoſe Reaſons that ſort of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration was laid aſide, and the other publiſhed, which onely pardoned the ſubmitting Commoners their Lives, but left all of the better ſort to the Rage of the Soldiers, and the Penalty of forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Rebels.</p>
                     <p>Upon the Publication of this, all the Gentlemen, and Landed Men, finding what they were to relie upon, combin'd with great Reſolution to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their Countrey, by a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Reſiſtence: So that we are like to loſe many thouſand of Lives, e'er they be reduced to the condition they were in, in <hi>July</hi> laſt, beſides the Expence of ſome Millions of Treaſure.</p>
                     <p>Surely, if the putting an end to the Wars in that Kingdom had been ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely intended, it had been no difficult matter to have penned a Declaration in ſuch Terms as might have effected it: We have ſeen modern as well as old Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents of Declarations, which have ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected great Deſigns, when they were no whit obſerved, after Poſſeſſion of what the Prince aimed at.</p>
                     <p>But, as if it had not been ſufficient to debar the better ſort of all hopes of ſubſiſtence, an after Declaration was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon, at once to impoveriſh the whole Body of the Commoners, more than if they had paid twelve Subſidies, and that was by debaſing the Braſs and Copper Coine.</p>
                     <p>In the time of K. <hi>James</hi> this Money was made currant, and the Soldiers were paid in it, and once in a Month, or ſo, the Pay-Maſters took in the Braſs-money from Suttlers, or others who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it from the Soldiers, if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired an Exchange, and they received Gold or Silver for it. But this Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation ſinking this Braſs Money to the intrinſick Value, whereby every 20 <hi>s.</hi> was ſcarce worth 2 <hi>d.</hi> it was ſuch a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den impoveriſhing of the Common Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and Tradeſmen, as was unſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: So that this ſo wiſely contrived Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, by little and little, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Conſent is little obſerved; for I am informed, by one lately come from <hi>Dublin,</hi> that a Crown of that Coine of K. <hi>James</hi>'s now paſſeth for 4 <hi>s.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I think very few will judge theſe two Proclamations to have contributed any thing to the Reduction of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but rather to the exaſperating the whole Body of the Nation, even to the <hi>Rapparies;</hi> and I am well aſſured, that one whoſe Pen was uſed in the draught of theſe, is ſo ſenſible of the miſchievous Effects of them, that he wiſheth he had loſt the fore Finger of his Hand, when he was ordered to write them.</p>
                     <p>But theſe have not been the onely <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moras</hi> of annexing that Kingdom to this Crown, but the fatal Council of laying Siege to <hi>Limmerick,</hi> hath impeded it more than any thing hitherto. If the Army had marched to <hi>Cork</hi> and <hi>Kingſale,</hi> thoſe two important Places might have been reduced in ſix hours, without the Treaſure that has been ſince expended in order to reduce them; and then we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44173:4"/> had ſooner been Maſters of all the Ports towards <hi>England,</hi> and the famous Road of <hi>Kingſale</hi> might have been a ſecure Harbour for our Fleet, and by a Block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ade <hi>Limerick</hi> might have been kept from doing miſchief, and a Siege laid to it at a more ſeaſonable opportunity.</p>
                     <p>From all theſe inſtances I think it may rationally be concluded, that ſome Peoples deſigns have been to keep up the Trade of War. I cannot condemn Foreigners, or Souldiers of Fortune; by ſuch arts they are enriched, without much hazard: but I think the wiſdom or integrity of our Countreymen, who are conſulted in ſuch matters, deſerves no great commendation from any who love Settlement and Peace rather than War and Confuſion.</p>
                     <p>But ſurely it behoves all Members of the Commons Houſe, who are choſen as the Tutelars of their Countrey, to make a ſtrict enquiry into theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and be well ſatisfied in the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of the late Moneys, by which a great many are known to have mightily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed their Fortunes, while ſo many Countrey Farmers, Houſekeepers and Tradeſmen are reduced to Alms, and ſo many true Proteſtants plundered and abuſed by our outragious Foreigners and profligate Engliſh Souldiers, as the Eminent Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> of <hi>Hilsbury</hi> can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, where they cut in pieces the very Hangings and Curtains to make Bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches thereof; neither did the Lady <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trim,</hi> the Lady <hi>Arglaſs,</hi> or that ancient Gentleman Sir <hi>Butler,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the near relation he hath to the D. of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and his Protection granted, eſcape any better.</p>
                     <p>But to finiſh the matter of <hi>Ireland:</hi> It is true, new Supplies under the E. of <hi>Marlborough</hi> are ſent, but that is done for another end, that the Dutch may be tranſported back hither, as Perſons more to be confided in here, and to be taken more care of, it being more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the grand deſign, that <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> may deſtroy one another, provided that the Pretorian Band of Foreigners be preſerved.</p>
                     <p>I now come to the ſecond Head; wherein I ſhall endeavour to prove, that notwithſtanding our giving of Money, as liberally as deſired, we cannot expect to give any great ſtop to the French K's Conqueſts, as Matters now ſtand.</p>
                     <p>I intend no Panegyrick on that great King, though, if he were not our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, he might deſerve it above any of his Predeceſſors. I think it cannot be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralleled in Hiſtory, that he ſingly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Conjunction of any other Prince, ſhould maintain a War in his Enemies Country, againſt the whole Empire, the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> Us, and <hi>Savoy:</hi> So that he is entirely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with the potenteſt Enemies that any Country was ever begirt with; and yet notwithganding, no one of them have been able to make an Impreſſion upon him, but he hath defended himſelf, and annoy'd his Adverſaries with a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs beyond the expectation of Mankind.</p>
                     <p>The D. of <hi>Savoy,</hi> ſollicited by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and <hi>Spain,</hi> and incourag'd by our Mony, hath been the lateſt who entred into Confederacy againſt him, and is like ſo be the firſt who will repent it, having very nigh loſt his Dukedom, as it was, before, to K. <hi>Henry,</hi> Grandfather to this preſent French King.</p>
                     <p>The States cannot be able to ſubſiſt long. A moſt intelligent Gentleman, who attended our Army in their Service this Spring, told me, <hi>That one of their conſiderableſt Magiſtrates told him, that they would uſe their utmoſt Effort this Summer to maintain the War; but if they had not ſome extraordinary Succeſs, they muſt make the beſt Terms they could; for they were no longer able to ſuſtain the Charge of it, conſidering the loſs of their Trade.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>What ſhall we therefore judge they can do, ſeing they never ſuffered ſo great a Loſs ſince they were a free State, as they have done this Year at <hi>Fleury,</hi> and at Sea, except when this very King over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run almoſt all their Countrey, <hi>Holland</hi> it ſelf ſcarce excepted; the preventing of which deſtruction was aſcribed to the interpoſing of K. <hi>Charles</hi> II.</p>
                     <p>As to their exceſſive Taxes I ſhall give but Two Inſtances,</p>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:44173:4"/>
                     <p>The firſt I had related from a Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man here, who received it from his Correſpondent there, <hi>That a Gentleman having the Tuition of two Orphans, paid the whole annual Income of their Eſtate, which was</hi> 1500 <hi>Pounds a Year, and this Year being aſſeſſed</hi> 500 <hi>Guilders more than the laſt, was forced to yield up his Tuition to the Magiſtrates.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The other is what the firſt mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Gentleman told me, <hi>That while he was there very many gave over their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Trades, by reaſon of exceſſive Taxes. He knew ſome Coffee Houſes, who paid</hi> 50 <hi>Pounds for Licence for one Year, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Tax according to the Rent of their Houſes, upon their Trades, and perſonal Eſtates, with the general Exciſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe, I hear, are Preſidents inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be follow'd in Raiſing of Mony here, together with a new Impoſition on Chimnys, to be purchas'd at ten years value, and the Sale of ſuch confiſcated Eſtates in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as are not receiv'd for the Uſes before ſpecifi'd. But I think theſe two laſt will find few Adventurers.</p>
                     <p>How the States, or at leaſt the <hi>Dutch</hi> Seamen, will reſent the Lord <hi>Torring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton's</hi> ſuffering them to ſuſtain the Loſs on our Coaſt, without affording them Relief, we ſhall not know, till there be ſome Joint Engagement againſt the French Fleet, eſpecially ſince after ſuch, upon the whole, I do not wonder that we have ſuch Rumours of the Dutch Endeavours to make a ſeparate Peace, as they did once, when they were in League with the Emperour and King of <hi>Spain,</hi> leaving them in the lurch. And it is to be ſuſpected, that if the States indeavour it not ſpeedily, the Rable will compell them to it; for it is well known that there ſtill remains a Party there, who never loved the P. of <hi>O.</hi> and are no better inclin'd to him as King.</p>
                     <p>As to the Emperour, this Years Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of the <hi>Turks</hi> in <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania,</hi> muſt neceſſitate him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to a Peace, either in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> or with the <hi>Port.</hi> The latter he cannot effect, as Matters now ſtand, upon ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Terms: And the <hi>Venetians</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing animated by the taking of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Place, <hi>Napoli di Malvaſia,</hi> will be very ſollicitous to purſue their good Succeſs with all Vigour imaginable on their Side; and we may be aſſured that the Pope, being ſo deeply intereſted in the advancing the Proſperity of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick, will leave nothing unattempted to induce the Emperour to proſecute the War againſt the Infidels, rather than here. And the <hi>Germane</hi> Princes, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently haraſſed by the War with <hi>France,</hi> wherein they have ſuffer'd ſo much Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Devaſtation, even to the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Contributions beyond the <hi>Rhine,</hi> will gladly embrace the Overtures of Peace with that Crown, eſpecially fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that this Year, hitherto, they have not been able to perform one Action, the Benefit whereof may countervail the Charge of one Brigade of their Army.</p>
                     <p>Farthermore, it is to be conſider'd, how diſadvantagiouſly the Confederates make War againſt <hi>France:</hi> The ſeveral Princes are neceſſitated in their ſeveral Diſtricts, to obtain the conſent of their reſpective States to raiſe Mony; after which there muſt be an adjuſting of all Things by Plenipotentiaries. or Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of thoſe abſolute Princes, by which means they are generally ſo late in the Field, that the <hi>French</hi> King ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects a great part of his Deſigns, e'er they come from their Winter Quarters. And when they are advanc'd, the Princes have almoſt as many independant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, as they have Armies; and it is well known with what Difficulty the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Princes,</hi> eſpecially the Emperour, raiſeth Mony to maintain ſo expenſive a War. Wheras 'tis certain, the <hi>French</hi> King hath made a ſecure Fund for nine Years beforehand, to defray all the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and contingent Charges of the War, and can with the ſame facility renew it at the Expiration of that Term, by a ſingular Way he hath above all other Princes, that even in times of Peace the whole Revenue of his Kingdom comes into his Exchequer every 4 or 5 Years.</p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:44173:5"/>
                     <p>He ordereth his Armies by his own ſingle Command, without any other co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Power, or dependence on the Suffrages of others, whereby all his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs are managed with ſecrecy and ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs. From whence we muſt conclude, that he is likelier to weary out the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, even upon the Defenſive part at their Charges, than they are to gain any Advantage upon him, even though we were able to provide our <hi>Quota</hi> of the Expence, and ſupply freſh Armies in conjunction, and according to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igence of the Confederates.</p>
                     <p>But what can we hope to doe, when the Sheaf of Arrows is unlooſed, and any of the Confederates ſhall make a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Peace? Can it be conceiv'd that we can be able to cope with the French K. when the Circumvallation is broken, and he ſhall be at Liberty to turn an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interrupted Force upon us; when we are exhauſted by Taxes, and ſo divided among our ſelves upon account of the Intereſt of King <hi>James,</hi> and the ill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding betwixt the Ch. of <hi>England</hi> and the Diſſenters, the Monarchical and Common-wealth Men?</p>
                     <p>The Caſe being thus, I think we ought ſeriouſly to conſider for whoſe Cauſe we began the War: It was firſt proclaimed here; and it was one of the great Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſores, both to the French, and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, that King <hi>James</hi> would join with neither Party; but that he deſigned to have ſtood neuter. But the States and Confederates found a means to make him flie for Refuge to that Prince who ſolely was not an Enemy to his Perſon, and was likelieſt to protect him, though he had declined to join in a League with him; which, as matters fell out, had been his onely Security.</p>
                     <p>So that upon the whole we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the Revolution here was the Contrivance of the Confederates, but principally of <hi>Spain</hi> and the States, to make a powerfull Diverſion againſt <hi>France,</hi> and engage us in their Quarrel; and to add the whole Force of <hi>England</hi> to their Defence.</p>
                     <p>Since therefore the War was begun, and is continued for the Advantage of the States, and thoſe Princes, and hath been ſo deſtructive to our ſelves, that, as it is managed, beſides the ineſtimable Loſſes we have ſuſtained, we are forced to contribute ſo great a ſhare of our own Money to ſupport them.</p>
                     <p>It cannot but be thought moſt advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable, before you conſent to raiſe Money, to ſend Commiſſioners to the States, to know whether they be able and willing to continue the War, and ſuch onely to be ſent, who may diſcover the Secrets of their Councils, and their Strength; and if they find them in both agreeable to our Wiſhes, then to know what ſhare they will bear of the Expences; for it is but reaſonable, that as we ſuſtain all this Miſery and Damage for their ſakes, and in ſubſervience to their ſingle Intereſt, they, and not we, ſhould bear the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</p>
                     <p>For to tell us at this time of the day, that we have put K. <hi>William</hi> upon the War, is a cold Conſolation, and an ill Requital for our Eaſineſs to ſubject: our ſelves to Dutch Stratagems.</p>
                     <p>If therefore the States and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates will pay the Debt of four Millions, be it more or leſs, I think our Country Men will be content to ſubmit to the raiſing a Fund of two Millions more for the next Compaign, and upon no other Terms, I think, it can be adviſable to grant any Money at all, nor then, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a juſt Account of what is expended.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was ſomething more added, but it was onely Aſſurance of Friendſhip, and that it was from an earneſt Deſire to ſerve his Countrey that he had compoſed it: Such therefore as it is I ſend you, and judge you will think I have fully obey'd your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, who am,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours aſſuredly.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
